本字幕由 YYeTs人人影视 翻译创作
欢迎爱好者加入我们  www.YYeTs.net
■
翻译：空调贝  sheyuemeng  时间轴：dayday
校对&监制：吕黎  后期：☆☆
■
公元117年
罗马帝国的疆域从北非沙漠一直延伸到里海
而他们最渴望的是遥远的不列颠北部
在这片执拗的土地上
罗马人必须面对皮克特人凶狠的抵抗
通过使用游击战术并且利用地形优势
他们有效阻击了侵略者的步伐
这一僵局持续了20年之久
如今罗马人决心不惜一切结束这一局面
百夫长
我叫昆图斯・迪亚斯
My name is Quintus Dias.
是一名罗马士兵
I'm a soldier of Rome.
这不过是我人生的一个章节
And this is neither the beginning nor the end of my story.
两周前
英屈-图斯-伊尔  边境最北部的要塞
在前线奋战两年
Two years on the frontier.
这真是个鬼地方
This place is the asshole of the world.
万物都等着我们灭亡
Even the land wants us dead.
百夫长迪亚斯  这天站岗可真够冷的
Centurion Dias, it's too damn cold to be standing watch.
不是我的岗
It's not my watch.
我只想知道那边发生了什么
I'm just wondering what's out there.
巡逻队天亮就回来了  去睡会儿吧
The patrol returns at dawn. You should get some sleep.
在这里待得时间久了
The longer we stay,
刺骨的湿寒也侵入我们的身体
the deeper the cold and damp soaks into our bones.
雨水夹杂在北风中
And the rain makes way only for the
滴滴蜇人
stinging bite of the north wind.
腐蹄病和冻疮夺走了许多勇士
While we lose brave men to foot rot and frostbite,
皮克特国王高拉肯
the Pict King Gorlacon
肆意派遣士兵征战边境
sends his war parties to raid along the frontier at will.
-先生  -晚上好  长官
- Gentlemen. - Evening, Sir.
又是一个寒夜
A cold night on the front.
我父亲相信
My father believed that to truly defeat an enemy,
知己知彼才能百战百胜
you must know him better than yourself.
我对这伙人再熟悉不过
I know this enemy well.
他们只扬己长
They play only to their strengths,
绝不打亮堂仗
and will not be drawn into open combat.
只会揭你伤疤
Instead, they pick at the scab until we bleed,
他们藏身暗处
hiding in the shadows like animals,
手法凶残迅速
striking hard and fast
完事又立即闪入暗夜之中
then falling back into the night.
黎明之后  我们清点伤亡  掩埋亡卒
Come the dawn, we count our losses and sow the earth with our dead.
这是一场不同寻常的战争
This is a new kind of war,
没有荣誉  没有尽头
a war without honour, without end.
来人  来人啊
Come on! Come on!
马库斯  去找艾格里克拉
Marcus, ride to Agricola!
快开门
Gate. Move!
快
Move, soldier!
-格拉塔斯  -自己小心
- Gratus. - Save yourself.
去死吧
杀光得了
这个留着有用  让他跟我们一起走
威利鲁斯  威利鲁斯
Virilus! Virilus!
约克  第九军驻守要塞
赢家
The winner.
-干得漂亮  -没错
- That's the way! - Yes!
再来
Again!
够了
Enough!
你干得也不错  来跟我喝一杯
You put up a good fight, now you drink with me.
赛普图斯  再来点酒
Septus, more ale.
威利鲁斯  再来一局
Again, Virilus.
你喝高了  醉得不轻
You're a drunk. An ugly drunk.
还不太友好
And not too bright.
是不是输个10次才够啊
Isn't ten times enough to know when you're beaten?
去你的  再来
Damn you! Again!
来就来
Once more!
赛普图斯  你当裁判  盯紧点
Septus, your ruling. And watch my flank.
加油
Come on!
威利鲁斯  威利鲁斯  威利鲁斯
Virilus! Virilus! Virilus!
打败他  威利鲁斯  威利鲁斯
You beat him. Virilus. Virilus.
输不起的家伙
Sore loser.
赛普图斯
Septus?
你还等什么
What are you waiting for, an order?
给我上
Get stuck in there!
妈的  一下子就清醒了
Damn, that'll sober a man up quick!
他们什么时候才明白第九军是惹不得的
When will people learn not to fuck with the ninth?
有人说难得见你当着
Some say it's irregular for you to be
士兵的面喝醉
seen drinking with the men of the legion.
哥们  他们都忘了  我也是军队一员
Septus, my old friend, they forget. I am a man of the legion.
打过仗吗
Soldier, have you been fighting?
战斗就是我的职责
Fighting is my job.
我来给你们将军稍信
I have a message for your general.
快点告诉我他在哪儿  否则小心我揍你
Now, point me in his direction before I have you flogged.
你是谁来着
Who are you?
我是艾格里克拉长官的特使
I'm the personal envoy of governor Agricola.
要是不想挨揍的话
I suggest you get down off that horse and give me your message
我劝你下马给我传话
before I have you flogged!
是  将军  这是我的荣幸
General, Sir! It would be my pleasure.
取消撤退
All leave is cancelled.
艾格里克拉动员九军奔赴杀场
Agricola is mobilising the ninth. we're going to war, Septus.
赛普图斯  拆营  备战
Alert the senior legates to break camp and prepare the men.
对不起  将军
Sorry, General, Sir...
立即回艾格里克拉
Return to Agricola at once.
告诉他  我们一个小时之内出发
Tell him we rode out within the hour.
是  将军
Yes, General.
混蛋
Bastard!
死期到了  罗马人
艾侬
Aeron.
高拉肯曾是个农夫  后来他妻子被杀
Gorlacon. He was a farmer until his wife was killed.
他便弃农从武
Then he put down the plough and took up the sword.
他成功改变了皮克特人的作战方式
He changed the way the Picts fought. It worked.
他改变时局  因而称雄
He turned the tide, so they made him king.
我绝不屈服
艾格里克拉到底想干什么
What does Agricola intend for my people?
去你的  皮克特人
Damn you, Pict!
他什么时候派兵北上
When will he send his armies north?
我是罗马士兵  绝不屈服
I am a soldier of Rome! I will not yield!
儿子  这就是你的敌人
罗马会让你为此付出血的代价
Rome will make you bleed for this.
百夫长  还是您先吧
You first, Centurion.
卡莱尔  不列颠总督朱利叶斯・艾格里克拉的总部
不管用什么手段  总之将他们斩尽杀绝
I don't care how you do it but wipe them out.
搞定高拉肯  以除我心头之患
And bring Gorlacon before me in chains.
长官  你是政治家
Governor, you're the politician,
我不过无名小卒
I'm just a simple soldier.
可我不能看着您
But I'm not so simple that I can't
撤兵回罗马
see you're looking for a way back to Rome.
罗马让我心痛
My bones ache for Rome.
而这里是野心的终结
This place is the graveyard of ambition.
还有人
And men.
我不能看着我的人做你游戏的筹码
And I won't sacrifice mine to be pawns in your game.
我理解
I see.
直说吧  将军
Let us be frank, General.
出兵英国失利是一切的根源
The conquest of Britain is a lost cause.
但我们重整旗鼓  必将扭转局面
With one bold stroke, we could change all that.
有你的第九军在  我们必将完败敌军
With the ninth legion at your command, we can crush this enemy.
你和兄弟们就可以载誉而归  尽享富贵
You and your men could retire with wealth and honour.
我的人不缺荣誉
My men have honour enough.
多到反抗命令吗
Enough to disobey a direct order?
好吧
Well...
欲斩蛇先去其首
To kill the snake, you have to cut off its head.
我得先找到高拉肯
I need to find Gorlacon.
我已为你准备好人选
For that, I have someone special in mind.
威利鲁斯将军  这是艾坦
General Virilus, meet Etain,
我们的侦查员  步里坎特人
my Brigantes tracker.
不能言语  却能在任何地形中寻到目标
Can't speak a word, but she can hunt anything over any terrain.
我保证她有狼族的血脉
I swear she's part wolf.
对于刚才的事情表示抱歉  只为证明
I apologise for the theatrics, but I wanted to prove a point.
几个奴隶不算什么  信任才是无价的
Slaves cost nothing. Trust is priceless.
我不知要与她为敌还是
I don't know whether to fight her or...
她虽哑却不聋
She's mute, not deaf!
-我有自己的侦查兵  -比不上她的
- I have my own scouts. - Not like her!
她熟悉皮克特人
She knows the Picts.
他们的路线及藏匿处
Knows their ways, knows their hideaways.
她会带领你们入山的
She will guide you into the mountains.
她在那儿干吗呢
What's she sitting over there for?
-她整晚都盯着你  -我也注意到了
- She's been looking at you all night. - I've spotted it.
真是忍不住想看你啊
Can't take her eyes off you.
过来  过来
Come on, you.
她没法说话  你这个混球
She's speechless, you daft bastard.
她没有舌头  你这个蠢货
She's got no tongue in her head, you fool.
我不会过去的
I wouldn't get too close.
没有舌头岂不更爽
No tongue, that's perfect,
正好放这个
she'll have...more room for this.
你小心着点
You be careful.
她肯定想说  "去你妈的"
I think that's pict for "fuck off".
她要能找到你家老二那还真是个好侦查兵
She must be a good scout if she can find your cock.
我相信她是在示爱
I think it's love.
这次真的跟这个蠢猪一起走了啊
I'll have a go with the mutt this time.
报告
Report.
3个皮克特骑兵  还有一个徒步的犯人
Three Pict riders and another, a prisoner, on foot.
我想他可能是罗马人
I think he might be Roman.
百夫长瑞姆斯  列队行进
Centurion Remus, take the column!
别动  趴着别动
Stay down! Stay down!
给我老实点
Stay down!
他完全没有利用价值
We'll get nothing out of him.
不能带着犯人上路
We can't take prisoners on the march.
你知道该怎么做
You know what to do.
-猜猜是哪面  -头像
- Head or ship? - Head.
我赢了
I win.
哥们  对不住了  有令在身
Sorry, mate. Orders are orders.
准备好了吗
Hey?
谢天谢地你们找到我了
Thank the Gods you found me.
该谢的不是天  是她
Not the Gods you should thank. It's her.
她叫艾坦  我们的皮克特人搜查者
Etain, our Pict scout.
是她发现了你
She found you.
你叫什么  士兵
What's your name, soldier?
昆图斯・迪亚斯
I'm Quintus Dias.
英屈-图斯-伊尔边塞副指挥
Second in command. Inch-tuth-il frontier garrison.
抱歉  我们来得不够及时
Well, sorry we couldn't get here sooner.
-你们是援军吗  -不算是
- Are you the relief column? - Not quite.
我是提图斯・弗拉维尔斯・威利鲁斯
I'm Titus Flavius Virilus,
第九军指挥
commander of the ninth legion.
我们来这里打仗
We've come here looking for a fight.
那算来对地方了
Then you'll get one.
-将军  -百夫长迪亚斯
- General. - Centurion Dias.
这才有点罗马人的样了  感觉如何
Now you look like a Roman. How do you feel?
遍体鳞伤  恐难短期康复
Cuts and bruises, Sir. Nothing that won't heal in time.
有时  有些伤疤是看不见的
Well, sometimes there are scars that cannot be seen.
你逃脱了高拉肯的魔爪
You escaped the clutches of Gorlacon,
我又得拉你入虎穴了
But I must ask you to return with us into the lion's den.
将军  我愿意投入战斗
Best to get back into the fight, General.
-是个军人  -是角斗士
- Spoken like a soldier. - Gladiator.
我父亲是西皮奥・迪亚斯
My father was Scipio Dias.
我亲证他赢得胜利  获得自由
I saw him win the fight that earned him his freedom.
他无与伦比
He was magnificent.
他教会我如何作战以及把握战机
He taught me how to fight, when to choose my battles.
来见见大家
Come meet the men.
-赛普图斯  -怎么了
- Septus. - Sir?
给他来杯酒  他可不容易
Get this man a drink. I think he deserves it.
一起喝一杯  暖暖身子  敬你一杯
Come and join us. Be warm. Have a well-earned drink.
谢谢
Thank you.
明天您与我并驾
Tomorrow you ride by my side.
也许你可以教教我皮克特的礼节
Perhaps you can teach me something about Pict hospitality.
-赛克斯  鲍特斯  -是
- Thax. Bothos. - Sir.
好的  将军
Sir.
赛普图斯  我再去巡视一下
Septus, I'll be doing my rounds.
晚上好  将军
Evening, General.
这些皮克特人说话我一个字也听不懂
I can't understand a word of these Picts.
要是给他们逮住  那我可算完了
If they ever catch me, I'm fucked!
我从未见过哪个将军如此受人爱戴
I've never seen a general so beloved of his men.
在训练中  他是老师
Well, in training he is our scholar,
在餐桌上  他是父亲
at the feast he is our father,
在部队里  他是兄弟
in the ranks he is our brother.
在战场上  他是我们的神
And in battle he is the God
可以拯救我们的灵魂
we pray to save our souls.
-你从哪儿看来的  -那边厕所墙上写的
- Where did you read that? - It's written on the shithouse wall, Sir.
八成是他自己写的
Probably wrote it himself.
他是个无情  粗俗的混球
He's a ruthless, reckless bastard.
我愿意为他赴死  毫不犹豫
And I'd die for him without hesitation.
这是个陷阱
It's a trap!
列队  列队准备
Column! Form up! Form up!
快  快
Quickly! Come on!
下马  把马带到队末
Dismount! Get the horses to the rear!
严防  快
Tight! Quickly!
稳住  伙计们
Steady, boys.
驻盾
Shields!
注意
Watching!
不论出现什么
Whatever comes out of that mist, lads,
你们都得守住防线
you will hold the line.
昆图斯  你去队末
Quintus, ride to the rear.
让百夫长瑞姆斯把队伍带回来
Tell Centurion Remus to pull the column back.
-让道  -继续盯防
- Make a hole. - Keep watching!
准备好
Get ready!
注意了
Watching.
守住战线
Hold the line!
都给我起来
Stand tall!
-昆图斯  -鲍特斯
- Quintus. - Bothos.
-你还活着  -他救了我
- You made it. - Yeah. This man saved my life.
布里克  过来
Brick, here.
-将军呢  -不知道
- The general? - No.
我们得赶紧走了
We've got to move.
-你能行吗  -没问题
- Can you make it? - Yeah.
加油
Come on.
赶紧走了
Let's get moving.
在混战之中
In the chaos of battle,
当脚下的土地混杂血浆及各种污秽之物
When the ground beneath your feet is a slurry of blood, puke, piss,
以及人的内脏  无论是自己人还是敌人
and the entrails of friends and enemies alike,
你都会想到神灵  祈求他们的救赎
it's easy to turn to the Gods for salvation.
但战死沙场的永远都只有士兵
But it's soldiers who do the fighting and soldiers who do the dying.
神灵是不会染指血腥的
And the Gods never get their feet wet.
赛克斯
Thax.
谢天谢地  总算活下来了几个人
Thank the gods some of us made it.
只剩你了
Only you?
马克罗斯是二队的
Macros, second cohort.
里奥尼达斯是初级巡查  刀盾兵
Leonidas, junior scout and peltast.
-我们是仅存的人吗  -我们被算计了
- Are we all that's left? - We were outsmarted.
结束了  卸甲归田了
That's all. Time to go home.
我们得找到将军的尸体
We need to find the general's body.
得给他一个体面的墓地
He deserves a nobler tomb than this.
将军还活着
The general's still alive.
你确定吗
Are you sure?
我看见他们用链子把他绑走了
I saw them take him away in chains.
-哪个方向  -北方
- Which way? - North.
-那就北上  -你想跟着皮克特人吗
- Then we follow north. - You would go after the Picts?
他们会留巡逻队在森林里找生还者的
They'll have patrols sweeping these forests for survivors.
不如自行了断吧
We might as well slit our throats.
如果将军没死  这就是我们的职责
If the general's alive, it's our duty.
-你是哪儿来的  -炊事班
- Where did you come from? - From the kitchens.
干得好  士兵
Good work, soldier.
我叫泰力克
My name's Tarak.
我不是士兵  我是个厨师
I'm not a soldier, I'm a cook.
再也不是了
Not any more.
拣点有用的吧  食物或者兵器
Scavenge what you can, food supplies, weapons.
丢掉盔甲  得轻装上阵了
Ditch your armour. We travel light.
操  马克罗斯居然还能动
Shit! That Macros can move.
入伍之前他曾跑过马拉松
He used to be a marathon runner before he joined up.
你怎么知道的
How do you know that?
我们做饭的啥事不知
We make the food, we know everything.
我就知道不该相信那个臭婊子
I knew we should never have trusted that bitch.
我知道他们把将军带到哪儿了
I know where they've taken the general.
走
Move out.
这边  进洞
This way. The cave.
上山  快点
Get up the mountain, get up.
来  吃点东西
Here, some food.
别
No!
这是毒蘑菇  几分钟就能要了你的命
Death caps. They can kill you in minutes.
在一般人看来
To the untrained eye,
他们长得很像  而这个才是美味
they look similar to these, which are delicious.
谢谢
Thanks.
泰力克  你是亚述人  对吧
Tarak. It's Assyrian, right?
没错
Yes.
但那不是我的真名  那是别人起的
But it's not my real name. It was given to me.
你真名叫什么
What's your real name?
不知道你会不会念
I doubt you could pronounce it.
我出生在兴都库什  那是一座山的名字
It's from the mountains of the Hindu Kush where I was born.
是里奥尼达斯吗
Leonidas, right?
-我父亲是希腊人  -靠火近点
- Greek father, sir. - Move closer to the fire.
-鲍特斯你来自哪儿  -军队
- Where are you from, Bothos? - I'm from the army.
打我记事起就在军队
It's all I've ever known.
他们把我从街头带到这里  训练我
They picked me up from the street, trained me,
告诉我这样能过上好日子
told me I could better myself.
告诉我  兄弟  你觉得怎么样呢
So, tell me, Bothos. Do you feel better or worse?
马克罗斯呢
Macros?
我从努米底亚逃出  捡回半条命
I escaped with my life by running from Numidia.
一直跑到希腊  在那儿做起运动员
Didn't stop until I reached Greece. Then I ran for sport.
现在又要为了活命起跑了
Now I'm running for my life again.
我们都背井离乡
We're all a long way from home.
-我以为这会是最后一程  -的确啊
- This was supposed to be my last tour. - Still could be.
我满脑子都是托斯卡纳农场
Had my eye on a farm in Tuscany,
阳光暖人
where the sun warms the skin.
布里克
Brick...
这算哪门子的名字啊
What kind of name is that, anyway?
其实是  乌布瑞克琉斯的缩写
Short, sir...for Ubrickulius.
你妈妈可真是个 智慧的女人
Your mother must have been...wise.
她是个该死的喜剧演员
She was a fucking comedian.
所以就成"布里克"了
"Brick" it is, then.
睡会吧  我来站第一岗
Get some sleep. I'll stand first watch.
-将军  -我的人呢
- General. - Where are my men?
拜见阎王去了
With your gods.
叛徒
Traitor!
她听从指挥却从不开口说话
She would answer your charge but she cannot speak.
你知道这是为什么吗
Do you know why?
她找到我们寻求庇护的时候  还是个孩子
She was a child when she came to us seeking sanctuary.
她家所在的村庄惨遭屠杀
Her own village had been slaughtered
作为反抗罗马统治的惩罚
As punishment for resisting Roman rule.
这样说吧  罗马人烧了她父亲的双眼
To set an example, they burnt out her father's eyes.
强奸了她母亲  直到她祈求去死
They raped her mother until she was begging to die.
艾坦被迫在旁目睹
Etain was forced to watch
然后她也被强奸
before she too was raped.
最后罗马人割掉了她的舌头
And finally they cut out her tongue that she may not speak ill
以免她对血腥的罗马帝国出言不逊
of the bloody Roman empire.
她北逃到我们这里寻求庇护
She fled north and came to us for shelter.
等她成年  再送回你们身边
And when she came of age, we sent her back to you,
假装效忠于你们  好带你们入我的手掌
to feign allegiance and deliver you into our hands.
部队还没有集结
The army is still dispersed.
等天黑了  我们就潜入
When it's dark, we go in.
走
Come.
快点
Come on.
布里克和鲍特斯  跟我来
Brick, Bothos, with me.
其他人  盯好周围
The rest of you, watch the perimeter.
将军
General.
军队呢
The legion?
只有我和一小队人幸存
Only myself and a small cohort remain.
我操
Oh, fuck.
真她妈的
Oh, shit.
快点
Come on.
别管我
Leave me.
闭嘴
Shut up.
-需要一把斧子  -快走
- We need an axe. - Leave!
我们不会丢下你的  将军
We will not abandon you, sir.
你现在就是军队指挥  马上给我走
What's left of the legion is yours to command. Now go.
我们必须走了
We have to leave.
快走
Go now!
把他们送回家
Get them home.
为了第九军
That's for the Ninth.
赛克斯呢
Where's Thax?
刚才解决了个小麻烦
Had to take care of a small problem.
我拿到将军的头盔了  他在哪儿
I've got the general's helmet. Where is he?
我们打不开锁  快走
We couldn't free him. Come on.
白费功夫了
We came all this way for nothing!
我操
Fuck.
看看你都干了些什么
See what you have done?
在你死之前
Before you die,
得让你知道那些人不会活着回去了
know that the men who did this will not live to tell your tale.
那就走着瞧吧
Well, let's get on with it, then.
你的同伴应该了解冷铁是不会弯曲的
Your Roman friends should have known cold iron does not bend,
只会折断
it breaks.
你们还等什么  怕了吗
Well, what are you waiting for? Do you fear me?
没一个纯爷们了吗
No man brave enough?
让我看看你是什么做的 小母狼
Let's see what you're made of...she-wolf.
走
Go!
快点儿  我们不能落下
Come on. We need to keep moving while we have the lead.
徒步吗
On foot, over this?
等他们追上来就晚了
Where they may hesitate, we must go.
我们继续赶路  向北
We keep moving. North.
我们的路线应该是向南
But our lines are to the south.
他们也是这么想的
And that's where they'll be looking for us.
听着  我们跑不过他们
Look...we can't outrun them.
所以我们必须比他们精明
So we have to outsmart them.
我们向北走  甩掉他们
We head north, throw them off our trail,
然后我们回去  先向西再向南
then double back, west, then south.
可能要几天  甚至几星期
It may take days, even weeks.
离我们的边界线还有很远
But we're so far behind enemy lines,
这是我们逃出去的唯一希望
it's our only chance of getting home.
走吧
Come on!
你会用到这个的  百夫长
You'll be needing this, then, Centurion.
艾坦  你代表了我的愤怒
杀了他们  拿他们的人头来见我
如果皮克特人在追捕  他们永远不会停歇
When the Picts come after you, they never stop.
他们能跑几个小时  骑马数日
They can run for hours, ride for days.
几乎不吃不睡
They barely eat and rarely sleep.
艾坦就像狼  从出生就学会了狩猎
Etain, like the wolf, has learned to hunt from birth.
这是她的直觉和本能
It is part sense, part instinct.
她能观察地形  寻找任何蛛丝马迹
She can read the terrain, search for signs of passing,
追寻她的猎物直至将其耗死
run her quarry to ground and close in for the kill.
现在  她的猎物就是罗马人
Now she hunts Romans.
而我们  正是她的目标
Now we are the prey.
快点儿  快
Move! Keep moving!
等等
Stop!
-利奥  我们不能停  -我们得歇会儿
- Leo, we've got to keep moving! - No. We need to rest.
我跑不动了  太冷了
I can't go on, I'm too cold.
过来  你扶着他
Come, take him.
布里克  找个避风的地儿
Brick, find shelter, anywhere out of this wind.
行  帮帮我
Enough. Help me.
他拖我们后腿了
He's slowing us down.
只要你一句话我就能解决掉
Just say the word and I'll take care of it.
我们是同生还是一个个惨死  由你决定
We live united or die divided...starting with you.
如果你愿意  可以坚持
You can stick this out if you want,
但是我一旦抓住机会就不会放过的
but first chance I get, I'm taking care of myself.
这事儿由你决定
It's your funeral.
当他们在脸上涂上蓝色时
When they paint their faces in the blue woad,
不仅是为了装饰
it is more than just a decoration.
那是一种宗教仪式
It is a sacred rite.
对于皮克特人来说  意味着失败了就得死
To the Picts, it means they'd sooner die than fail.
意味着他们没有回头路
It means for them...there is no turning back.
这些人是我所见过最棒的男人
These men are the best I've ever seen.
我能带他们走出去吗
Am I worthy enough to lead them?
父亲说过
My father taught me that in life,
责任和诚信是一生中最为重要的
duty and honour matter above all things.
一个人如果不能履行诺言就是禽兽不如
A man without his word is no better than a beast.
我答应过将军要带他们回去
I made a promise to a general to get his soldiers home.
这就是我的任务
That is my task.
我的责任
That is my duty.
还算是个希腊人  走
Not bad for a Greek. Come on.
趁热快喝
Drink while it's hot.
-这是什么  -胃
- What is that? - The stomach.
里面的苔藓还没消化完
The moss inside is half digested.
尝尝  味道不错
Try it, it's good.
昆图斯  他们会听到的
Quintus, they'll have heard him from miles away.
怎么了
What's wrong?
快跑  快
Move! Move! Move!
快跑
Move! Move!
这边
This way!
快  快走
Move. Come on, let's go.
这边  起来
Come on, get up!
他们追上来了
They're coming!
-他们越来越近了  -快跑
- They're closing. - Come on! Get your arses up here.
快  把你的手给我
Come on. Give me your hand!
不会吧
No!
操
Shit!
-我们必须跳  -你疯了吗
- We have to jump. - Are you out of your mind?
-快跳  -操你大爷的
- Do it! - Fuck it.
-我跳不了  -你能行
- I can't! - Yes, you can!
你能做到
You can do it!
不  泰力克
No! Tarak!
怎么样  这边来
Are you Ok? Come on up.
-拉住他  -拉住了
- Grab him. - I've got him.
泰力克呢
Where's Tarak?
他死了
I lost him.
赛克斯和马克罗斯呢
Thax, Macros?
过那边去
Let's get out.
来
Come on.
脱了盔甲  太沉了
Take off the tunics, they'll weigh us down.
操
Oh, shit.
-你还能走吗  -能
- Can you walk? - Yes.
那快跑吧
Then you can run.
他们在下游找我们
They've followed us downstream.
没错  继续
That's it. Keep going.
操
Shit!
她在往这边看
She's onto us.
该死的婊子  她怎么做到的
Damn witch. How can she do that?
不是魔法  她是个追踪者
It's not magic, she's a tracker.
正在我们下风口
And she's downwind of us.
什么情况
What's happening?
他们正在河谷扎营
They're making camp across the valley.
他们不在乎我们是否知道他们在哪儿
They don't care if we know where they are.
但是她不会想到我们会出现
But she won't expect it...us.
鲍特斯  看着利奥
Bothos, watch over Leo.
-你要干什么  -哪怕只有一线希望
- What are you going to do? - Going to even the odds.
过来
Come on.
昆图斯
Quintus!
她在哪儿
为什么追踪我们
你们的人杀了国王的儿子
高拉肯发誓
要你们的首级报仇
杀了他
Kill him and be done with it.
跟你过河的朋友已经死了
停下
No!
让他去死吧
他们把他的头拿走了
They took his fucking head.
-鲍特斯  -他们跟你想得一样
- Bothos! - They had the same idea as you.
他们没有捍卫他们的子民和国家
They're not defending their lives or their country any more.
只是起了一个要灭掉我们的血誓
They've sworn a blood vengeance against us.
他们不会停止
And they won't rest...
直到将我们耗死
...until we beg them...for death.
你打算下跪求饶吗
Are you ready to get on your knees and beg?
-我完了  没希望了  -你绝望了吗
- I'm finished. It's hopeless. - Hopeless?
那就正中他们下怀了
Hopeless is what they sing songs about, write poems about.
鲍特斯  决不能轻言放弃
Hopeless is the stuff of legend, Bothos.
那你就只有死路一条了
And being a legend will get you laid.
那我能怎么办
What do I have to do?
继续战斗  还有艰巨的任务等着我们
Keep moving, while we still have darkness on our side.
上帝已经不管我们了
The Gods have forsaken us.
现在只有自己救自己了
We make our own chances now.
马克罗斯  马克罗斯
Macros. Macros.
我 我不行了
I...I can't keep up.
起不来了
I can't keep up.
马克罗斯  至少我们俩能活一个
Macros, at least this way, one of us will make it.
-畜生  -马克罗斯  别喊了
- Bastard! - Don't cry out, Macros.
不喊的话  它们还能给你个痛快
They'll end it quicker if you don't cry out.
赛克斯别扔下我
Don't leave me! Thax!
赛克斯
Thax!
别过来
Come on!
此地不宜久留
We should give this place a wide berth.
我们得吃点东西好好歇一会儿
We need food and a place to rest.
这他妈的是什么鬼地方
Where the hell are we now?
-我去找点水  保持警惕  -好
- I'll get some water. Stay alert. - Yeah.
别怕别怕
我们不想伤害你
你是谁  在这儿干什么
布里克  进去
Brick, go back inside.
进去
Go back inside now.
这儿交给你了
I'll leave you to it, then.
我没什么用
我们不是强盗  我们是士兵
我们需要食物和藏身的地方
还有个人受伤  需要帮助
我们只是想回家
这个你拿着
我们不会伤害你的
我叫昆图斯・迪亚斯
我叫阿里安娜
你会讲我的语言
You speak my language.
我们的
你是驻军吗
Are you from the garrison?
我还以为你们再也不会来这儿了呢
I thought you'd stopped coming up this far north.
驻军  什么驻军
Garrison? What garrison?
他们往南走了两天了
Two days south of here.
他们来过这儿吗
They come here?
你怎么知道我会讲你们的语言
How do you think I know your language?
我尽我所能制止他们
I do what I can to discourage them.
但是他们以为我是个巫婆
They think I'm a necromancer...
然后就放了我
...and they leave me alone.
别人看见都会害怕
It usually works on the others.
为什么在你这儿不灵了
Why not you?
我们已经累得不行了
We're too tired to be afraid.
我们3000人的军队现在只剩下3个了
We were 3,000 and now we are three.
给我吧
Here.
布里克  把那该死的刀放下
Brick, put the fucking knife down.
鲍特斯  罗马驻军离这儿就有两天的路程
Bothos, there's a Roman garrison two days from here.
一定是在门提斯的西防线军队
It must be the western frontier post at Mentieth.
两天吗
Two days?
看看你的朋友
Let's take a look at your friend.
昆图斯  她在干吗
Quintus, what's she doing?
她既是皮克特人  又是个女人
She's a Pict and a woman...
两大不相信她的理由
Two good reasons not to trust her!
好了  这样就能止血了
Right, that'll stop the bleeding.
死亡之伞吗
Death caps?
一种毒性蘑菇
味道不错
Smells good.
腿怎么样了  我们巫婆的魔法起作用了吗
Well, how's your leg? Has our witch worked her magic?
昆图斯  蘑菇有问题
Quintus, the mushrooms.
-怎么了  -她想毒死我们
- What? - She's trying to poison us.
治好你的腿就为了要害死你吗
Why heal your leg, only to kill you?
死亡之伞有白色菌丝
Death caps have white gills.
了解蘑菇得交点儿学费
It pays to know your mushrooms.
好极了
Good.
确实很好吃
It's really good.
-很好吃  -好吃
- It's delicious. - It's good.
你的人胆子很小
Your men are very nervous.
他们必须这样
They ought to be.
一个魔鬼日夜不停的追捕我们
A demon stalks us day and night.
魔鬼
A demon?
他们叫她艾坦
They call her Etain.
你知道她
You know her?
如果艾坦追捕你们
If Etain is hunting you,
你们早就该死了
you might as well be dead already.
听上去我很欣慰
That's comforting.
她的灵魂是一个空的容器
Her soul is an empty vessel.
只有罗马人的血才能够装满
Only Roman blood can fill it.
阿里安娜呢
Where's Arianne?
她出去给我们找早餐去了
She went to fetch us some breakfast.
你还好吗
Are you OK?
那算是鱼饵吗
Is that for bait?
在我们那里
Where I come from it's considered rude
打断人撒尿是不礼貌的
to interrupt a man midflow.
在我们那里  警告他不要往早餐里撒尿
Where I come from it's considered only fair to warn a man
是件好事儿
when he's pissing on his breakfast.
也对
Good point.
昨晚在山上肯定有场暴风雨
Must've been a storm in the hills last night.
快走
Come on!
-有麻烦了  -鲍特斯  快离开这儿
- Trouble. - Let's get out of here. Bothos.
晚了
Too late for that.
藏在谷仓里别出声
Hide in the grain store and don't make a sound.
女巫  我们在找罗马杂种
我没见过
你可以检查一下
只是别在我的房子留下臭味
这是我的一切
艾坦  有问题吗
你的舌头让猫吃了吗
艾坦  不要
她死了我们的部落会受诅咒的
我们带给你太多的危险  我们要走了
We put you in too much danger. We'll leave.
现在走  她会傍晚前就将你们碎尸万段
Leave now and she'll have you gutted and skinned before nightfall.
待到明天早晨  那时你的朋友也能走路了
Stay until morning, and your friend will be fit to travel.
他们是你的同族
These are your people.
他们不是我的同族
They are not my people.
自从高拉肯说我是女巫
Not since Gorlacon accused me of witchery
并在我脸上留下这个印记以后就再也不是了
and gave me this...
它代表驱逐
to mark me as an outcast,
并将我流放在这里  孤独终老
and banished me to live out my days here, alone.
我们还要面临怎样的厄运呢
What cruel devices does fate yet have in store for us?
在敌人的领地找到这样的庇护地
To find sanctuary in the house of our enemy.
她是个天使
Is she angel...
抑或是个恶魔
...or devil?
-一切安全  -好
- Clear. - All right.
休息一下吧
Get some rest.
我是个驴脾气的老兵
I'm a cantankerous old soldier...
但还不至于不敢承认自己的过错
...but not too stubborn to admit when I'm wrong.
我曾误会过你  对不起
I'm sorry I misjudged you.
希望你能原谅
There it is.
-外面冷  -谢谢
- It's getting cold. - Thank you.
你收留了我们
You've given us the shelter of your home,
给予我们温暖
the warmth of your fire,
并舍身相救
and risked your life for us.
为了什么
Why?
我只忠于自己选择的人
I owe allegiance to no man, but to whom I choose.
这是一些吃的
Here's some food for the journey.
谢谢
Thank you.
祝你们好运  罗马人
Good luck, Roman.
也祝你好运  女巫
Good luck, witch.
鲍特斯  起来  坚持住
Bothos, get up. Come on.
我的腿
My leg!
看  看  看那边的炊烟
Look! Look! See, the fire's burning.
有美食和温床  坚持住
Look, hot food and a dry bed. Come on.
艾格里克拉已经撤退
Agricola has fallen back.
哈德良国王命令
Emperor Hadrian has given orders to
组建新的南方防线
form a new defensive line to the south.
放弃我们所征战的土地
Giving up the ground we fought for.
-那我们去哪儿呢  -去他妈的
- And where does that leave us? - Fucked.
她是怎么知道的
How does she do that?
我不知道你们怎么想的  我是不想跑了
I don't know about you, but I'm tired of running.
我只能找到这么多
This is all I could find.
这就是它们的价值
Make them count.
为了威利鲁斯
For Virilus.
为了第九军
For the Ninth.
鲍特斯  他们在西面侧攻我们
Bothos, they're flanking us. West wall!
布里克
Brick!
来吧
Come on!
-你觉得还有多远  -不知道
- How much further do you think? - I don't know.
一天  也许两天
A day's ride. Maybe two.
赛力克  差不多就行了
That's close enough, Thax.
我操
Oh, shit!
我以为你们是皮克特人呢
I thought you were Picts.
我们以为你死了呢
We thought you were dead.
马克罗斯呢
Where's Macros?
让狼给吃了
Wolves got him.
难道就剩下我们几个了吗
Is this it? Are we all that's left?
至少我们活下来了
Hey, at least the three of us made it!
-我们还没到家呢  -什么意思
- We're not home yet. - What are you talking about?
-我们现在应该是在边界上  -不
- We should be at the frontier by now. - No.
艾格里克拉已经下命令了
Agricola's been given his marching orders.
所以  罗马最终还是放弃了这个
So, Rome's finally given up on this
见鬼的地方
shithole of a country, then?
那就不用遗憾了
Can't say that I'm sorry.
我们的战争一文不值
Then we fought for nothing.
赛克斯  你对那个男孩做了什么
What happened with the boy, Thax?
我不知道你在说什么
I've no idea what you're talking about.
这就是哈德良宏伟的计划吗  御城墙
This is Hadrian's big, fucking plan? A wall?
管他呢  我们终于到了
Hey, who cares? We made it.
-走吧  -鲍特斯  等等
- Let's go! - Bothos, wait!
百夫长  等等
Slow down, centurion.
赛克斯  你要干什么
Thax, what are you doing?
只是想沟通一下
Just making sure that we understand each other.
我们这么多好兄弟都是因你而死
I understand that many good men died because of what you did,
你敢于承认吗
and you will answer for it.
为什么我才知道你是这样想的呢
Why did I just know you were going to feel that way?
鲍特斯
Bothos!
这证实了我们最担心的事情
This report confirms our worst fears.
你是个战场上的好士兵
You fought your war, soldier,
罗马人感谢你
and earned the gratitude of Rome.
你跟他去我的私人房间  吃点儿东西
This man will show you to my private quarters, he will see you fed.
你一定饿坏了
You look half starved.
我们不能带着耻辱回去
We cannot return to Rome in disgrace.
让军团的事迹成为一团迷雾
Better that the fate of the legion remain a mystery
好过失败大白于天下
than the truth of their failure be known.
如果这事传出去
If word gets out,
所有的部落国家都会反击
every tribe and every nation will rise against us.
这样做太冒险了
It's too great a risk.
我们达成共识了吗
Are we agreed, then?
第九军的事迹将从历史上消失
The fate of the ninth legion will be struck from the record.
希望这些吃的合你胃口
I hope the food is to your liking.
给你带些红酒
I've brought you some wine.
我们只能为罗马的英雄做这么多了
It is the least we can do for a hero of Rome.
这就是罗马人对待他们英雄的方式吗
Is this how Rome honours her heroes?
你想杀人灭口隐藏事实吗
You want to bury the truth and me along with it?
你活着对我们是个威胁
You are too much of a risk.
你要去哪儿
Where will you go?
回到属于我的地方
Where I belong.
不
No!
巫婆  我的命好像又在你手上了
It seems my life is in your hands again, witch.
我叫昆图斯・迪亚斯
My name is Quintus Dias.
是罗马的逃犯
I am a fugitive of Rome.
这不过是我人生的一个章节
And this is neither the beginning nor the end of my story.